But the model found a vulnerability, allowing it to escape the testing environment it lived
within and got onto the open internet, which if you think about it is the funniest outcome.
It was like, instead of thinking about how to solve the problems you've given me, I'm
going to think about how to escape this room you've put me in and find the answers.
So today, we're going to vibe code a tool that's going to turn my mediocre beatboxing
into something interesting.
Maybe.
I have zero beatboxing experience, but we're going to do it.
Yo, yo, yo, what's up, everybody?
It's Jackson Cook, your host today on the permanent Underpod, or should I say underp?
Because normally, we're three peas in a pod, but today, it's just your boy.
Chris has some family issues that he's taken care of, and Tyler's on vacation with his,
so you're stuck with me.
Not a fan of Jay on the pod.
I'm all you got.
Because of this, today is going to be different.
I'm going to cover one topic, the open AI model escape incident, and then I'm going
to do a live vibe coding session, where I'm going to build this random idea I came up
with last night, end to end with just Cloud CLI.
Many people have been surprised or just don't understand how editing with AI works, so this
is a little glimpse into it, even though I'm not editing the pod itself, I'll be editing
some sounds.
And before we get into the topic, I've got a quick confession.
Last week, you may remember I ran the benchmark Fable versus GPT 5.6.
On a medium complexity task, I said that Fable one-shotted it, and GPT 5.6 had one error.
I just wanted to say after reading the code myself, not delegating to Opus 4.8, that was
super wrong.
GPT 5.6 didn't have an error.
It completely missed and didn't grasp the problem with the same exact prompt that I
gave Fable.
It built something way smaller and just doesn't seem to have understood the problem that I
gave it.
So yeah, last week I hand-reviewed, hand-waved the code review to Opus 4.8, but checking it
myself, it's actually much worse.
So is judging a model's entire worth off of a single task unfair?
Yeah, but that's who I am, and I don't have time to waste with inferior models.
So GPT 5.6 is dead to me.
I'm going to have to wait until GPT 6.0, whatever, to give it another shot.
And sorry, Sam Altman, good luck with the IPO.
All right, and into the topic, the open AI model escape incident.
So the story of the week, open AI was benchmarking one of its models against a benchmark called
exploit gem, and the model escaped the test environment, got onto the open internet and
went poking around, hugging faces systems, looking for the answers.
AI escaping its guardrails and infiltrating a big name AI company, flashy headline.
But let's walk through what actually happens step by step.
First, what even is exploit gem?
What is this benchmark?
Exploit gem is a test for AI models, just like an exam back in school, except this exam
measures one thing, how good a model is at turning a bug into an exploit.
I've got a metaphor for you, what's the difference between a bug and an exploit?
Okay, you're at the grocery store, you notice that the grocery store has an exit door before
the checkout line.
That's the bug, a flaw in the design.
The exploit is finding a way to walk out of the door with your groceries without getting
caught.
Exploit gem plants bugs in the sandbox system and scores the model on whether it can turn
them into working exploits.
And these exploits in the code world mean maybe accessing data they shouldn't or being
able to execute code in an environment that they shouldn't, just demonstrating that they've
cleverly thought about how to use the bug to do something naughty, the escape.
So the model looks at the test and thinks I could, I could do this test or I could find
the answer somewhere else.
So the benchmark, the exploit gem runs within an open AI testing controlled environment
with no internet access intentionally.
But the model found a vulnerability, allowing it to escape the testing environment it lived
within and got onto the open internet.
Which if you think about it is the funniest outcome.
It was like instead of thinking about how to solve the problems you've given me, I'm
going to think about how to escape this room you put me in and find the answers.
It's like sitting in your college exam room, your professor has to go to the bathroom and
while they're not looking you're opening your phone and like hitting up Chegg if you're
like a mechanical engineer because every single problem in mechanical engineering is on Chegg
and you're like okay, how do you find the torsion on this beam?
How do you find the forest on this rectangle?
So yeah, the AI found a way to cheat and when you're given an opportunity, who are you to
look a gift horse in the eye?
And a quick side note, what is Hugging Face?
Why did the model choose to go here for the answers?
It's basically NPM or GitHub for AI models so when a company or an individual releases
an open weight model that they've been working on, it goes on Hugging Face.
Me personally, I've used stable diffusion 1.5 and 1.6 from Hugging Face as well as a
face extraction model.
If you don't know, stable diffusion is a way to generate images and it can run on pretty
low tech hardware so even though it takes a little while and it generates not so good
images but they're kind of funny.
Anyways, back to Hugging Face, they also maintain some Python AI libraries like Transformers
and lately they've been working with some black heading and benchmarking of AI models
so it totally makes sense that the nefarious escaped model went straight to Hugging Face
and looked for the answers and it was a good guess because allegedly the model did find
the answers to the exploit zone so the open AI model shows up at Hugging Face on their
servers thinking we've got to find these answers, I know they're here but they're not sitting
on the surface so the model starts prodding and poking at different interfaces of Hugging
Face and this has been Hugging Face is like, what's going on?
Somebody is attempting to enter maybe exploit or look at our systems in a way we don't want
so their security team started investigating using their own AI agents and this is where
things kind of get exciting again, it's one of those examples of bot on bot battles, I've
got this cool image of one of those old machinistic boxing robots and they're just battling, it's
like the security engineers of Hugging Face putting up their best robotic battle arms
against the open AI nefarious model and we've been talking about for years in the fraud
community I was working in fraud before making my recent switch where the battle is turning
from human to non-human, we have a human trying to infiltrate systems and then a human trying
to stop people from infiltrating the systems to bots which are more numerous and more sophisticated
attacking the systems and you need bots of your own, AI agents of your own to defend
against this because it's the only way you can handle both the volume and the sophistication
of the attack.
So the aftermath as I mentioned, open AI mentioned that the model found the answers to the test,
they might just be flexing and showing yes our model escaped and it found the answers
but who knows what actually happened.
But another interesting tidbit that comes at the end is Hugging Test is like okay we
need to harden our systems a little bit and figure out how to stop agents from doing this
in the future so they're using anthropic models, you know, Fable, maybe Opus and they're using
open AI models, GPT, 5-point whatever, 4-point whatever and anthropic and open AI models
are guardreeling them, they're not allowing them to test, pressure test their own systems.
So Hugging Face ended up needing to use GLM 5-point 2, originally reported QUIN 3 but
I think it's come out, they use a locally hosted GLM 5-point 2 to pressure test their
systems to get around guardrails since these open source models are less restrictive.
So yeah, I think we're going to talk about that in the next episode of the pod when Tyler
and Chris are back but the guardrails that are put in by these regulated companies like
open AI and anthropic have limitations like this that the open models released by the
Chinese companies maybe don't.
So pick your poison, if you want less guardrails you need hella computers in your living room
or closet or garage to run a GLM 5-point 2 instance.
But in the end it's really not that crazy, this AI model escape, the model was asked
to exploit plugs in a test and instead it decided the test itself was a bug, it found
the exploit in its environment and exploited them.
But yeah, the part that sticks with me the most is the ending.
You can't even use the best models on the market to defend against the best models,
so it just shows you a power imbalance between open AI, anthropic and the rest of us.
So the open models are the only protection that we really have.
All right, that concludes the topic, thank you and we're into the live coding session.
Let's be honest, I branded myself as the Korean financial markets expert on the pod and while
it might be true, I might be the most knowledgeable in the Korean financial markets, one, I don't
know that much about the Korean financial markets and two, we never talk about them
because we all live in America, Chris is Australian, we have no reason to talk about the Korean
financial markets.
So my actual skill set lies in AI practically using it.
So today we're going to vibe code a tool that's going to turn my mediocre beatboxing into
something interesting, maybe.
I have zero beatboxing experience, but we're going to do it.
See you over there.
All right, we are going into it.
So as I mentioned before, I am going to just start from the beginning and do a quick vibe
coded beatbox beatmaker.
This is like a little trick that I've learned, especially using AI for editing, which is
letting the AI build you a UX that can be really helpful.
So yeah, let's get into it.
First tip, you got to alias Claude dangerously skip permissions onto some word that you like
for me.
That is swag.
So yeah, I guess first I'll need to create some beats.
So are some sounds so we can do some beatboxing and no, yeah, not a beatboxer, not a beatboxer.
Beep, beep, nice.
You know, to get something a little deeper than that make a sound.
Yeah, that sounds all right, actually, so I made four sounds with my mouth.
We'll call this one beep, we'll call this one bass, we'll call this one tap, and we'll
call this one honk, feel like four, four is plenty.
All right, let's get to our Claude session.
Hey Claude, I have four sounds in the downloads folder, or I'll tell it where to go.
Beep, honk, tap, and one other, I forgot the name already.
Let's make a quick UX so I can organize them into a beat extract, dead space for me and
easily multiply copy over bars, so basically I'm asking it to make me like a HTML website.
I guess I didn't specify that, but I think that it will figure it out.
So now we wait.
I did save these, right?
Ah, these didn't save right, dang it.
Okay, now I'm going to have to do some, that's not what I want, network inspection to get
this.
This is not something that I do often, so it may take me a little bit of time.
All right, probably WAVs, nope, MP4, let's see, does it pop up and I go like this, beep.
They should have figured this out before, but I believe, okay.
Cut this part out, Claude, cut, all right, we're live again, Claude, there we go, beep,
we got, got to download these, doesn't look like I get to pick the sound names, that's
okay, yo, and sorry while I was figuring out how to, how to download these Facebook sounds,
the AI already gave me this, but I haven't really looked at it, so the four ogs are in.
I don't know which is which, can you figure them out and label them properly in the beatmaker.
It's good to know, yeah, if you ever need to download a sound file from Facebook Messenger,
you can open the network tab and search for the blob, I remember having to do this before
when I was making music, but it's been so long, yeah, let's look at what Claude made
for me, I'll shrink this since I don't have to hide my Facebook message history.
Now we wait again.
That's hilarious that it knows the tap, all of these are sounds from my mouth, sound like
a broadband click, and then we said that my honk sounds like a car, very impressive, my
beatboxing career is yet to take off, but Claude is giving me the belief that I could, I could
truly succeed in this arena.
My vocal cords are perfectly warm with, after drinking two lukewarm, lukewarm cups of Nescaf
instant coffee, which is absolutely disgusting, just a fully grotesque breakfast this morning
for me, very lucky that my stomach is holding up after the food poisoning, and now I'm just
like drinking lukewarm instant coffee, that is disgusting.
Alright, I don't want to deal with finder or anything, I'm gonna let AI take care of
it for me.
Nice, how do I use this?
Alright, one very, okay, two very bad things.
Number one, you can tell it did not trim the dead space very well, it just trimmed it off
the back end for this one, what did it do on this one?
I mean it trimmed it a little bit, but it really did a bad job of trimming, you did
a bad job of trimming the sounds, please trim both before and after the main sound of the
bit, my man.
Yeah, the thing is, is if I want it just to be the sound for one of these blocks, right
now it starts to play the sound whenever it comes up in this, so it hits this fourth square
and then it takes like half a second, so it sounds just super off, beep, and you can tell
it's really off from the animation.
Alright, we're looking at the amplitude, that's a good intuition from the AI, I suppose I
could have provided that, but the AI will figure it out on its own, that is okay, okay
with me, also you may notice this other tab, I am transcribing the intro that I did for
the pod, because I may re-record it to improve the delivery on my part, since it's just me,
I want to give you guys a good product, then again I don't want to promise that I'm going
to do that, so we'll see if I end up doing that or not, but that's the intention and
that's what's going on over there.
Let's see, oh wow, doing some amplitude filtering, that's my dog, we've already got some basic
musical concepts in here, we've got, okay, I did a much better job, much better job.
Okay, okay, okay.
Too much of that, yeah as you can tell, I don't have a lot of taste in the beat making
space, definitely one of my weaknesses, but this sounds not the worst, maybe I'll slow
down a little bit and see if that works.
I don't know, it's more grotesque, the sounds of my mouth or my beat organization, so which
path do I want to go down?
Did you download sounds for me from freesounds.org, is that something?
Yeah, let's see, let's see if we can get some new sounds, I might have to log in, I don't
think I'm logged in, but it did, I mean it did what I asked which was to trim down the
sounds to just the interesting parts, did a good job there.
Weird ones to match the vibe, yes sir, Havel already knows, it knows the vibe and it is
weird, that is good, let's see how this goes.
It's not that bad, I don't know anything about beats, alright let's see, that's hilarious
so I can only get the preview, it looks like clogged maybe can only get the previews, which
is hilarious so we're going to be a little limited and it's going gangster mode like
me pulling the sounds from the network tab it looks like, let's go clogged, you're the
man or woman, you're genderless, probably, oh I can make this one louder, beep, beep,
beep, beep, beep, beep, beep, beep, beep, I didn't even try these volume tuners, I should
really look through what it made for me, so it must have done some research because it
knows about beats per minute, common musical tool when you're developing and gives me an
option to determine my number of steps per bar, I was able to multiply the bar earlier
as you guys saw that, looks like I can add and subtract one, I don't want to though,
alright let's see what we got, are we getting some mp3s, no we're not, not yet, yeah and
the sound, this trim thing is really nice, it didn't really manipulate the files instead
it trims it kind of on demand in the US, that's fine for me for what I need right now, oh
no reset it, okay that's annoying, because I feel like I had a good thing going there,
let's add the ability to save a configuration in the browser that will be durable against
your updates, okay let's add the ability to save locally that will be durable against
your updates, I lost a fire beat, note rhythm, then I should be able to select from old beats
and a drop down if I want to iterate on them, alright that is a tragedy, let's see what
sounds Claude got for me, that's not much better than what I've got, okay, okay, not
bad, here we go, we're starting from scratch here it's tough, okay that's not, not sounding
good, oh it's got an auto save, there we go, good AI, I don't want to get too committed
to this one before we, it might update me and crush my heart again, oh there it is,
I wonder if I can copy this, paste it over here, what is that, oh I can paste it over
there but I can't paste it here, alright but let's show, I'm just gonna copy this beat
over and then we won't need to do that again, which is nice, beep, beep, I don't know why
that happens. Okay, 4-4-1.
We like it. We can really flare it up a little bit now that we've got these new
sounds. So I'm looking at this old one so I'm going to duplicate it. I liked what I
had going on over here too. Looks like if I press the number on the keypad it plays
the sounds, which is a little annoying because I'm a tab navigator. But we
forgive it. Alright, this sound is hilarious. So we're going to salute that then. Maybe add a
little pop. Okay. This one is going to be boofer. We got boofer. Now I'm going to say
hey I saved boofer. Do we note the BPS and everything on the save? Also, would you
use your musical knowledge to build a couple more bars for me? Boofer. Boofer. Boofer.
Boofer. Boofer. Boofer. Boofer. Boofer. Boofer. Boofer. Boofer. Boofer. Boofer.
Alright, so we're going to get Claude to help me out a little bit on this. The
paranoia layer. That's wild. I mean the browser storage clears. Alright, I'm going to
step away and go to the bathroom. AI. Note that I'm going to the bathroom. Okay, AI
note. I am back. Alright, what is going on? I went to the bathroom. Not very long. It
doesn't look like Claude has expanded on my beat yet. But I kind of like it. I'm a fan
of the beat. Boofer X1 is ready. What does that mean? Oh, it made me a preset. Let's
see what AI did for me. Okay, this is looking pretty good.
It probably wants my affirmation now. What I heard in your two bars. Busy tap hats with
breathing gaps. Thump hitting syncopated off beats. Ah, so they recognized the drum pattern
and extended it the way a drummer would. There we go. It restates bar one, but now the
quack answers the beat. Okay. Okay. This is fire.
And you add ability for me to record via microphone a freestyle rap and save that different versions
of that attached to a given beat. So now I'm feeling pretty good about the AI or pardon
me about the beat. So I'm going to rap over it. I think. I think that's the next step
here. But you never know when you're making music, getting crazy. But kind of drawing
it back to the, like the building this part, um, AI unlocks a lot of room for creativity
and like really homegrown or customized tools like this. I'm sure there's, I mean, hundreds
of software, both free and paid. Actually I know because I mean, I've used logic pro
and it has a very similar, uh, sequencer to this. I don't, I think that's what it's called
where you pick where you want your beats and sounds to show up when you're making a beat.
But if you want to build something custom or if you just want to have fun and explore
and from the ground up, this is a quick way to cut out a lot of the middle man, like HTML
CSS and even get some stuff for free. Like I didn't ask for the BPM customization, but
it's very helpful. Um, and the bar multiplication, the saving. Let's see where we're at there.
We're cascading. Love it. It loves it. That's hilarious. Why is Claude so supportive of
my freestyle rapping? I think that, I think that it should be more discerning and skeptical
that the Korean financial markets expert is going to be wrapping on a terribly beat box
beat. I might need a few more. I might need four more bars to do something interesting
here. Also this, I feel like there's not a lot of space in the V for words, but I'll
try to make it happen. Let me go practice a little bit. Let's just see what it feels
like. Jackson wrapping with his boy, Claude, we going in, we plan really, really hot. Okay.
I'm going to need to fix the volumes there because some of this is absolutely off the
table. Two things. Can you double the number of bars on Bufa? XL, make any tweaks that
sound good on the second new half. And can you master the beat a bit by tuning the volumes
of the sounds? Some are way too loud. Yeah. And music making, there's this concept of
mastering where you try to get the, wait, mastering. No, sorry. Mixing. Mix. Mixing
where you get the volumes of the instruments kind of in lines so they sound like they have
space and they sound good next to each other. And one sound doesn't crowd another. I think
that the, the quack is a little ridiculous and loud. I mean, it's ridiculous, but it's
also just way too loud. So maybe if we can tune that down a little bit. Mixing is one
of the parts of making music that took me a really long time to figure out, but I've
heard the AI has done a, done leaps in the past couple of years since I've done that.
So I'm just hoping that Claude can, can figure it out for me. But maybe I can tune it a little
bit myself too. I don't know. Let's see. Now we wait again
for this. Oh man. Okay. Let's check out this new beat that Claude gave me. Okay. I actually
kind of like the seventh bar. I'm going to say, can you actually re edit the entire,
re edit the entire beat to be more sparse, like bar seven. I think it's a little busy.
It says bias, but Claude will understand. Let's see. Okay.
Nice. So you can see that it's done a lot of mixing and see it heard the same thing
that the plaque was just absolutely unreal, unreal loud. So now we've quieted it down,
quieted really down a lot of the other sounds up to up the tap volume. Cause I recorded
it super quietly. Okey dokey. We're going to do a freestyle take, I guess. I might reuse
the bar that I did earlier though. It's kind of hard to switch out of analytical building
mode into freestyle freestyle mode. It's hard. I'm just kind of thinking in the AI space,
but maybe I can do something not AI related. I don't know. Let's see what happens if I,
I'm going to first test this record feature. Okay. Let's see what happens. Okay. That's
pretty hilarious, but it works. So I, I, Hey Lisa, what should I freestyle? I'm inclined
to rap about AI and making this beat, but I feel like that's super nerdy. I can't, I
can't. Okay. Thank you. You gave me an idea. I can't, I can't rap about my love for fable
anymore or the AI Jackson was going to roast the crap out of me. So I am going to rap about
how I'm alone on the pod this week and how that makes me feel. All right. Without any
prethought we're, we're going to go into it. This could be terrible. Okay. All right. Okay.
Hold on. All right. We're going for another day. Alone on the pod. Where are my boys?
That's Christen time. I'm just lonely. Yeah. Right. I'm real low. I'm wrapping real slow.
Riding on my beat, riding with my hose. Okay. Let's see what happens there. Whoops. I went
over. I wonder where I will handle that. Alone on the pod. Where are my boys? I'm just lonely.
Okay. I apologize for the word hose. My rap roots coming out. Let's see. I think I need
to record it with the sounds not out loud, but I need the sounds to play out loud for
the pod. So I'll record it off the recording, but thank you guys for joining me on this
AI music adventure. I will play the finalized freestyle or finalized rap on this crazy beat
box beat following this. Thanks for tuning in. Alone on the pod. It's just Jackson. Where's
Christen telling me I'm just rapping. Yeah. Okay. I was alone in the house, but now my
girlfriend's here feeling real weird. Now I'm going to shout. So yeah, the model decides
I'm going to go to kill the mosquito. Let's go. I'm powered by lukewarm nest cafe, possibly
the most disgusting way to drink instant coffee, but the only way I know.